

Dr. Prabhat Shankar

Applied Data Scientist

♣ Profile

Data Scientist with 7 years of experience in Artificial Intelligence and Machine Learning. Have worked on algorithm development as well as product development for Industrial analytics. My experience ranges from different projects related to Data Science, predictive modeling, deep learning and developing flask APIs. I also lead a team of more than seven motivated data scientists.

Employment History

Industrial Analytics Solution Lead at ABB Ability Innovation Center, Bengaluru

June 2021 — Present

Leading the Data Science team in ABB for Industrial Analytics solution platform, providing cutting edge solutions for Time series Forecasting, Anomaly Detection, Outlier detection, Data Visualization and Processing.

- Leading the product vision, algorithm development, Flask API creation and product integration end to end.
- The product ABB Genix Platform has been highly rated in the industry for its intuitive and no code approach and democratizing the use of complex algorithms so that a layman can use it with minimal assistance.
- Executed different customer PoC in the domain of digital twin, optimization, Reinforcement learning.
- Integrated Generative AI approaches in the Predictive Maintenance Solution, leading to simplified user interaction and flexibility in product usage.

Senior R&D Engineer at ABB Ability Innovation Center, Bengaluru

September 2017 — May 2021

As a senior R&D Engineer, I worked on data science problems in ABB Robotics.

- Cloud based anomaly detection algorithm in Robotics Paint Systems.
- Pick and place operations in Robotics using Reinforcement learning.

Postdoctoral Fellow at RIKEN QBic, Kobe, Kobe

August 2015 — August 2017

As a Postdoctoral fellow at RIKEN, I worked for analyzing biological datasets to extract the hidden regulatory network in cellular systems. This work leveraged different Machine learning techniques, as well as the knowledge of dynamical systems and Boolean Networks.

Location: Bengaluru, India

Contact: +91-7337841021

Email: prabhat4686@gmail.com

Skills

Machine Learning

Predictive Modeling

Artificial Intelligence

Deep Learning

Large Language Models

Reinforcement Learning

Flask API Development

Pytorch, Keras, Tensorflow

Hobbies

Sports, Traveling, History and Culture

Education

Doctoral Degree: RIKEN QBiC, Kobe, Japan

2011 — March 2015

As a Doctoral Student at RIKEN Kobe, I worked on biological datasets to understand the regulatory mechanism of cellular systems. I learned the behavior of multiple types of networks, and applied Machine learning to make predictive models of biological systems and understand them better.

Bachelors and Masters: IIT Kharagpur, West Bengal

July 2005 — June 2010

Electrical Engineering

Patents Awarded

1. P180299IN01 - Granted - IN - 201841050077 - METHOD AND SYSTEM FOR DETECTING ANOMALIES IN A ROBOTIC SYSTEM

Publications

- 1. · Adaptive Responses limited by Intrinsic Noise: PLoS ONE 10(8): e0136095. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0136095
- 2. Binary decision of asymmetric or symmetric cell division by the balance of PAR polarity proteins: Yen Wei Lim1, Fu-Lai Wen, Prabhat Shankar, Tatsuo Shibata, and Fumio Motegi

Recognition and Awards

- 1. Secured Second place, out of more than 300 participants at the ABB Accelerator event, which is the annual hackathon to promote innovation.
- 2. Star First Line Manager Award, ABB
- 3. Junior Research Fellowship for Doctoral studies (2011-2014), RIKEN, Japan
- 4. Selected in Regional Mathematics Olympiad twice (state rank of 7&10).